Guide to the Records of the Grand Army of the Republic, James Monroe Post, No. 607 1862, 1887-1928 MS 3084
New-York Historical Society
Records of the Grand Army of the Republic, James Monroe Post, No. 607
1862, 1887-1928
New-York Historical Society
Grand Army of the Republic. James Monroe Post No. 607 (New York, N.Y.)
MS 3084
2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons.
The collection includes records of the Grand Army of the Republic's James Monroe Post, No. 607, in Manhattan, which was mustered in 1887. These records include the original roll of members, minutes of its meetings from 1895-1928, financial records, printed departmental and national orders, quartermaster reports, some letters, print ephemera, and other documents, especially from the 1910s-1920s. The women's auxiliary unit of the post is represented in the collection with some letters, financial reports, and in print ephemera.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format.
Biographical / Historical
The James Monroe Post, No. 607 of the Grand Army of the Republic, Department of New York, was chartered on November 17, 1886, and mustered on March 5, 1887. The post was comprised of veterans of the 22nd Regiment of the New York State Militia, which served in the Civil War for a few months in 1862 and again in 1863 as the 22d Regiment Infantry, N. Y. Volunteers. The post took the name of Colonel James Monroe, the commanding officer who died of an illness at Harper's Ferry, Virginia, on July 31, 1862.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John S. Van Etten, grandson of the post's last Adjutant, Josiah Clark Read, 1977.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes records of the Grand Army of the Republic's James Monroe Post, No. 607, in Manhattan. These records include the original roll of members at the post's muster in 1887 and minutes of its meetings from 1895-1928. There is an assortment of other records, such as financial records, printed departmental and national orders, quartermaster reports, a few membership applications, letters, print ephemera, and the post's American flag, though few of these have long or complete files, and much of the collection dates from the post's later years. The women's auxiliary unit of the post is represented in the collection with some letters, financial reports, and in print ephemera.
Patriotic societies -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Veterans.; Financial records.; Letters (correspondence); Minutes (administrative records); Printed ephemera.; Rosters.; Woman's Relief Corps (U.S.). James Monroe Corps No. 43 (New York, N.Y.)
- Minutes (3 volumes), 1895-1928 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1-3)
- Roll of members, 1887-circa 1915 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 4)
- Black list ( no entries), undated (Offsite-box 1, Volume 5)
- Ledger, 1887-1924 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 6)
  Scope and Contents
  Primarily includes dues payments, but also for tickets for installation of officers, post badges, and the like.
- Cash journal, 1903-1925 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 7)
- Checkbook, 1920-1924 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 8)
- Bible, 1912 January 19 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 9)
  Cover embossed: "James Monroe Post No. 607 from James Monroe Corps No. 118 [Women's Relief Corps]"
- Grand Army of the Republic, Headquarters. National orders, 1896-1906, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 10)
  Also includes three circulars from the National Woman's Relief Corps, Auxiliary to the G.A.R. Some additional orders are also found in the folder of correspondence below.
- New York Department, Headquarters. Orders, 1896-1906, 1917-1919 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 11)
  Some additional orders are also found in the folder of correspondence below.
- 50th anniversary souvenir, 1912 May 28 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  Booklet documenting the celebration of the 50th anniversary of the departure of the 22nd Regiment, N.G.N.Y, for the Civil War. Booklet includes documentation of the celebration and photographs of the parade.
- Rosters, circa 1920 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes a printed 1920 roster and handwritten rosters from perhaps the same timeframe or somewhat earlier.
- Quartermaster (financial) reports (2 folders), 1916-1924 (Offsite-box 2, Offsite-box 3-4)
- Photographs, 1862, 1918, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  1862 photo is of four members of the regiment at their tent in Harper's Ferry.
- Correspondence, 1916-1925 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  Primarily includes arrangements for memorial services, acceptances/regrets in response to various event invitations, and some bills/dues. Also includes an appeal to the U.S. War Department to award a Medal of Honor to Lieutenant-Colonel Asa Bird Gardiner.
- Applications and reports, 1916, 1919 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  Holds 2 applications, 1 report of officer election results, and blank forms.
- Post orders and other print ephemera, 1910-1922 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  Holds two orders issued by the Monroe post, memorial service programs, and other small printed items.
- James Monroe Corps, No. 118. Women's Relief Corps, 1916-1921 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  Holds several quarterly financial reports of the Relief Corps (1916-21) and some letters from the Corps to Commander Leggett of Monroe Post (1920-21).
- Remarks and obituaries, 1918, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Print matter. Grand Army of the Republic, 1908-1914 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  Holds booklets of rules and regulations, two copies of "rituals," and "services," and a certificate to Josiah C. Read.
- Print matter. Songs and poems, 1894, 1901, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
- Print matter. "The American Flag", 1910 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  Issued by the State of New York Education Department
- Print matter. Proceedings of annual encampment, New York (2 volumes), 1918, 1920 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14-15)
- Print matter. "History of the 77th Division.", 1918 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  Inscribed to the Monroe post by Archibald G. Thacher, a former major in the 77th Division.
- Artifacts. Gavel and copper plate (G.A.R. insignia) on wood block, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
- Artifacts. Monroe Post's American flag and smaller flags, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)